<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<poetic_corpus>
    <poem title="The Rock" author="Charlotte Perkins Stetson" date="">
         <![CDATA[
         I am the Rock, presumptuous Sea! 
         I am set to encounter thee. 
         Angry and loud, or gentle and still, 
         I am set here to limit thy power, and I will 
         I am the Rock ! 

         I am the Rock. From age to age 
         I scorn thy fury and dare thy rage. 
         Scarred by frost and worn by time, 
         Brown with weed and green with slime, 
         Thou may'st drench and defile me and spit 

         in my face, 

         But while I am here thou keep'st thy place! 
         I am the Rock! 



         I am the Rock, beguiling Sea!

         I know thou art fair as fair can be, 

         With golden glitter and silver sheen 

         And bosom of blue and garments of green. 

         ]]>
    </poem>
<poem title="In This Our World" author="Charlotte Perkins Stetson" date="">
         <![CDATA[
        Thou may'st pat my cheek with baby hands, 
	And lap my feet in diamond sands, 
	And play before me as children play; 
	But plead as thou wilt, I bar the way! 
	I am the Rock! 

	I am the Rock. Black midnight falls; 
	The terrible breakers rise like walls; 
	With curling lips and gleaming teeth 
	They plunge and tear at my bones beneath. 
	Year upon year they grind and beat 
	In storms of thunder and storms of sleet 
	Grind and beat and wrestle and tear, 
	But the rock they beat on is always there! 
	I am the Rock! 
         ]]>
    </poem>

  <poem title="The Sea" author="Charlotte Perkins Stetson" date="">
         <![CDATA[
        I am the Sea. I hold the land 
	As one holds an apple in his hand. 
	Hold it fast with sleepless eyes, 
	Watching the continents sink and rise. 
	Out of my bosom the mountains grow, 
	Back to its depths they crumble slow ; 
	The earth is a helpless child to me 
	I am the Sea ! 

	I am the Sea. When I draw back 
	Blossom and verdure follow my track, 
	And the land I leave grows proud and fair, 
	For the wonderful race of man is there ;
         ]]>
    </poem>
    <poem title="The World" author="Charlotte Perkins Stetson" date="">
         <![CDATA[
         And the winds of heaven wail and cry 
         While the nations rise and reign and die 
         Living and dying in folly and pain, 
         While the laws of the universe thunder in 

         vain. 

         What is the folly of man to me? 
         I am the Sea! 

         I am the Sea. The earth I sway; 
         Granite to me is potter's clay; 
         Under the touch of my careless waves 
         It rises in turrets and sinks in caves; 
         The iron cliffs that edge the land 
         I grind to pebbles and sift to sand, 
         And beach-grass bloweth and children play 
         In what were the rocks of yesterday; 
         It is but a moment of sport to me 
         I am the Sea! 

         I am the Sea. In my bosom deep 
         Wealth and Wonder and Beauty sleep; 
         Wealth and Wonder and Beauty rise 
         In changing splendor of sunset skies 
         And comfort the earth with rains and snows 
         Till waves the harvest and laughs the rose. 
         Flower and forest and child of breath 
         With me have life - without me, death..
         What if the ships go down in me? 
         I am the Sea! 
         ]]>
    </poem>
      <poem title="A Common Inference" author="Charlotte Perkins Stetson" date="">
         <![CDATA[
        A night: mysterious, tender, quiet, deep; 
	Heavy with flowers ; full of life asleep; 
	Thrilling with insect voices ; thick with stars; 
	No cloud between the dewdrops and red Mars; 
	The small earth whirling softly on her way, 
	The moonbeams and the waterfalls at play; 
	A million million worlds that move in peace, 
	A million mighty laws that never cease; 
	And one small ant-heap, hidden by small weeds, 
	Rich with eggs, slaves, and store of millet seeds. 
	They sleep beneath the sod 
	And trust in God. 

	A day : all glorious, royal, blazing bright; 
	Heavy with flowers; full of life and light; 
	Great fields of corn and sunshine; courteous trees; 
	Snow-sainted mountains; earth-embracing seas 
	Wide golden deserts; slender silver streams; 
	Clear rainbows where the tossing fountain gleams; 
	There is no God! 
	And everywhere, in happiness and peace, 
	A million forms of life that never cease; 
	And one small ant-heap, crushed by passing tread, 
	Hath scarce enough alive to mourn the dead! 
	They shriek beneath the sod, 
         ]]>
    </poem>

 <poem title="Songs" author="Charlotte Perkins Stetson" date="">
         <![CDATA[
         I. 

	world of green, all shining, shifting! 
	world of blue, all living, lifting! 
	world where glassy waters smoothly roll ! 
	Fair earth, and heaven free, 
	Ye are but part of me 
	Ye are my soul! 

	woman nature, shining, shifting! 
	O woman creature, living, lifting! 
	Come soft and still to one who waits thee here! 
	Fair soul, both mine and free, 
	Ye who are part of me, 
	Appear! Appear! 

	II. 

	How could I choose but weep? 
	The poor bird lay asleep; 
	For lack of food, for lack of breath, 
	For lack of life he came to death 
	How could I choose but weep ? 

	How could I choose but smile ? 
	There was no lack the while! 
	In bliss he did undo himself; 
	Where life was full he slew himself 
	How could I choose but smile ? 
         ]]>
    </poem>

 <poem title="This Our World" author="Charlotte Perkins Stetson" date="">
         <![CDATA[
         Would ye but understand! 

	Joy is on every hand! 

	Ye shut your eyes and call it night, 

	Ye grope and fall in seas of light 

	Would ye but understand! 
         ]]>
    </poem>

 <poem title="The Cup" author="Charlotte Perkins Stetson" date="">
         <![CDATA[
        And yet, saith he, ye need but sip 
	  And who would die without a taste? 
	Just touch the goblet to the lip, 
	  Then let the bright draught run to waste! 

	She set her lip to the beaker's brim 
	  It was passing sweet! It was passing mild! 
	She let her large eyes dwell on him, 
	  And sipped again, and smiled. 

	So sweet ! So mild ! She scarce can tell 
	  If she doth really drink or no; 
	Till the light doth fade and the shadows swell, 
	  And the goblet lithe low. 

	O cup of dreams ! cup of doubt! 
	  O cup of blinding joy and pain! 
	The taste that none would die, without! 
	  The draught that all the world must drain! 
         ]]>
    </poem>
</poetic_corpus>
